alright how's everyone doing today
welcome to nether I was not a research
club meeting today were talking about a
fusion in part 2 we're talking about the
combinatorics because last week we
talked about cat fusion protocol and we
have one of the authors with us journal
is with us today
who'll answer questions in just a moment
okay I mean we had a bunch of resources
because this was not a research so I
just want to clarify that Etan Hammond
u1 and Janet who Janet wrote a blog post
about the de nieve Cohen joins Matt
Eaton brought up two attacks and nothing
much actually brought up some attacks
and or you were naturally yourself to be
caught when he brought up some attacks
on and and was was writing very long
article yes so there's a lot that's been
said about the combinatorics and the
privacy and security of the comet or X
and so we'll be talking about that okay
here's the paper you can find it on
github and of course this is where we're
at with the research club so you can see
here last week we did a coin cash
shuffle or cash fusion the first time
okay we've been talking about coin
shuffle and plus plus in the previous
weeks and these were mostly about equal
output coin joints and we had a problem
that we hit which is that we want to be
able to do arbitrary amounts so the
problem is that when a user uses any
coin joint system that has a fixed
amount typically they get maymay points
later only to consolidate those coins an
arbitrary number of those coins without
revealing input ownership ideally and
those
their privacy so it would be great if we
had a protocol that allowed for
arbitrary outputs and arbitrary amounts
and last week Journal talked a lot about
how cash Fusion allows a trustless and
secure way for individuals to interact
and create this arbitrary input
arbitrary output point join by using
pretty clever trick with homework
property of Pearson commitments
Pettersen commitments and having all
user submit 23 input output or blank
values so they can have any number of
inputs and outputs or blanks as so long
as the sum of those is not more than 23
or the sum should be exactly equal to 23
and then other users can verify each
other if the protocol just fails to to
complete so one question we can ask is
okay well the entire protocol allows
users to submit an arbitrary number of
input outputs where the amounts can be
within a certain range but aren't fixed
as is in the case of zero link so how is
it possible that we can't link inputs
outputs if there are no equal outputs
like these other protocols and so this
is what we're gonna be talking about
today we need to understand two things
the bell number of a set of elements and
the subset-sum problem so I'll be going
over those and then we'll go into
questions for the authors and everyone
else so let's just take an example here
are some inputs and outputs and what
might be a cash using the coin joint and
purposefully doing a simple and small
coin joint so a real character you coin
joint is much much larger but this will
illustrate the point sufficiently so
here is the actual breakdown I've made
it very simple there are three
participants red orange and yellow and
if you do the math you will see that the
amounts are exactly equal we're not
considering fees at this moment but if
you're just a passive bystander this is
what you see right you see a bunch of
inputs you see a bunch of outputs and
you you have
right especially if you're a forensics
company you want to know what's going on
here so the questions you might have are
for example how many participants are
really here because this is just one
transaction it could be just one
dispense that's what you know a naive
onlooker might might think but you're
smarter than that you know there might
be more than one participant in this
coin joint and which input links to
which output so one way you might do
this is look at all the ways that the
inputs can be grouped and all the ways
the outputs can be grouped and try to
find a value much so so the question
arises well how many ways can we
partition a set into smaller non-empty
subsets and as an example let's just
focus on the outputs because there are
few fewer outputs that inputs in this
case there are just six so this seems to
be quite a trivial problem how many ways
can we dish in this set of six elements
into subsets where there are no empty
subsets well an obvious solution is just
you know what
once that is the entire set that's
obviously works and that would be the
case that this transaction only involves
one individual can also do set one and
set two like this we could do it like
this where or one set has three elements
another has two and a third one has only
one element and we don't care about the
order of the subsets we really only
concern distinct partitions so how many
ways can we rearrange these subsets such
that again their intersection is the
original set excuse me their union is
the original set for a set of six
elements there are total of 203 ways to
partition this set into subsets this
might be a surprisingly large number
we're going to talk about the number in
just a second so the number of waste a
set
any petitions is called the L number and
we can observe the Bell number as we
increase the number of elements in our
set so obviously if you have a set with
one element there's only one way to
Commission it which is that very element
and that's it if you have two elements
you have two ways to partition good
partition it so that it's both all of
its one element is in one second one
element isn't the other and so forth and
you can see that the bill number grows
very quickly so by the tiny if this to
do a set of seven elements you already
have almost a thousand ways that they
can be partitioned and there's a
recursive way that we can find a bail
number of any n plus one so long as we
know the total number of n of 0 to n and
here it is and what's more important to
sort of understand is that the bail
number grows very very quickly
so you see here on the right there's an
upper bound of you know this equation
with the with the diffraction and and
input simply it's it's it's rough please
you know it's less than n to the N so
it's a very very large number and so as
an example if you wanted to investigate
whinging with 100 inputs you have to
inspect this many possible combinations
so it's a very very large number as you
can tell so yes we go back to our
original coin joint and we say ok well
how many possible subsets do we have to
consider well over on the right we have
our bail number of six elements which is
203 and on the Left we have our bail
number of nine elements which is 21,000
so you can see it's growing very quickly
and in a very simple way this is
actually not true not the case we can
simply try the four million roughly 4
million combinations of subsets on the
left-hand subsystem there
the reason why this isn't true why do
little asterisks is because you don't
want to try an example where there are
three sets on the left and two sets on
the right because that doesn't make
sense the number of sets on the left and
the right must must match so it's
smaller than four million but as you can
see it's already quite large and the
idea that the authors of cash fusion
make the argument they make is that when
you have a large number of participants
with many inputs and many outputs as an
example they they said ten participants
with with ten inputs and ten outputs
each you start to get into numbers that
are just not practical for a forensics
company to it to unravel and now we have
to talk about the other problem which is
the subset sum problem so given a set of
numbers is there a non-empty subset
which whose sum is 0 so I'm gonna KP do
you'll find something like this you know
1 2 3 4 5 negative 3 negative 4 negative
8 and here are some examples of subsets
that add up to 0 now what the choroid
example that we were looking at we can
just treat the right-hand side as
negative the left-hand side is positive
and we get back to this this very
problem so ya solving the subset sum
problem so here's an example you know if
I wanted to solve this problem I just
found right now two inputs then output
that exactly match to the same value I
can just may many times and I can do it
with a very different complexities I
have many many inputs many output so I
could have just one input and one output
and so the question to ask is well
what's the complexity what's the runtime
for a computer to try to break and
investigate all of the input-output
pairs and essentially comes down to two
parameters and I pulled this directly
from Wikipedia so you'll read the same
they're essentially comes down to n the
number of elements you need to
investigate so when our cases the number
of inputs and outputs participants and
further P the precision and so it turns
out if you are less precise about
the sets matching that it's actually
quite quite a bit faster so the goal for
hiding in this complexity with doing
cash vision is to create many inputs and
outputs so make a large end and distort
the precision of the input output links
essentially having some sort of
randomized to ease which is what the
authors mentioned in the paper as a good
weight to distort the precision and so
algorithms for solving this subset some
run in exponential time which again is
what we're looking for for hiding in in
in complexity right we want something
that gets incredibly complex the more
participants join and so yeah that's
pretty much the the very basics I will
say a few things make a few points later
on but that's pretty much everything I
wanted to share to get us going so I'll
open it to jonald need to say something
and then questions yeah those are good
summary yeah so just to disclaimer I'm
like not a mathematician except but I
encountered this belt number when I was
just trying to research this a little
bit there's a lot of greats mouths
public a PDA anyway so yeah as you as
you played it out it's it's not like
exactly a belt number like it like feet
right but you could have a bell number
for the in fights like the number of
perdition's and then multiply that by
the by the outputs but then as you
mentioned like it wouldn't necessarily
be the same number of of groups in that
partition so there's a my kind of number
called a sterling not a murder which is
related to the bell numbers basically a
vowel number is like you're summing all
the Sterling numbers over over some
range so the way I thought to really
calculate it would be to like start with
start with the number 1 like 1
group and so the number of ways you can
divide like 50 outputs into one group is
going to be just one
and so you would multiply that by the
number of by the number of partitions
that have one group on the outputs then
you go to two and so you ask how many
ways can you partition this group of 50
inputs into two groups and so on and you
just keep going up until you've reached
either the number of inputs or the
number of outputs and then so you get
all those products and then you just add
them all together but it's very similar
to a goal number so yeah that's like
what and then basically what with what
the math and the paper is based on is
basically like comparing that number of
partitions to like the number of
possible values you'd have in the in the
space quote-unquote so for example let's
just say that you're the maximum value
out of any input or sum of inputs is
going to be like ten bitcoins or ten
Bitcoin cash so that's that's 1 billion
satoshis and so if you have like nine
players then instead of like ten to the
nine it's really like ten to the nine
times nine which is ten the 81 actually
you can take away one of the players
because the the last player will just
kind of have the leftovers
kind of like by default so you might
have with like eight ten times or some
ten to the eight times I which is ten to
the 72 so that's kind of like where
those numbers come from it's like you're
comparing like 10 to the 90th first is
10 to the 70th and so the all these
numbers are huge but the the number of
partitions is like order or so magnitude
bigger so like on a probabilistic level
you're bound to end up with a bunch of
valid partitions and then there's a
second way that I analyzed it which
which I wrote another article on which
is kind of a more straightforward
approach like let's start with player 1
have him select 10 of the 10 of the
inputs and outputs
and so he'll get like an N she's okay
number and then you go out of the next
player and but instead of choosing from
like 100 inputs he'll only have 90 to
choose from and you can do it that way
also and it sort of also you might now
put the same conclusion that it's
they're given the right size of the the
number of players and the precision of
the inputs and the applets they're going
to be it's it's basically private in
this way thank you before going into
specific points I'd like to give an
opportunity to eat an and nothing much
to do to comment on what what happened
what what they heard so far so maybe
let's start with eaten you have any
thoughts or comments so far yeah I guess
one thing that I'm kind of curious about
is it seems like these numbers are very
large but these seem like worst-case
analyses for instance you could imagine
a some subset problem that's actually
like really easy because the values
chosen are just like they just like
works out nicely so like one of the
problems that people have had when
trying to use the knapsack problem for
cryptography is a knapsack problem is
hard sometimes but most of the time it's
easy and so it seems to me like some of
these coin joints may provide privacy
and some of them may provide not privacy
or less privacy and I wonder how you
think about that gap between that like
the worst case numbers and the the like
best case where it is like trivial to
solve just because of the numbers that
are chosen yeah that's a good question
I I don't have like a like a simple
answer but but you are correct like we
just saw for example I think it was last
night there was this awesome looking
transaction with like 100 implants and
like 20 outputs but then there was one
input I forget it was either one
imported one output or maybe both I was
like
really big like like it was like eight
BCH when all the other ones were like
one BCH output so obviously that was
that one sticks out like a sore thumb
so then that's kind of one example of
the kind of thing you're talking about
and maybe there's others as well I think
what we could do at Subway is is to try
to put in what I call a sanity check
just like a some kind of filter where
you're looking for outliers and stuff
and I think the outliers is one thing
maybe there's like I said maybe there's
other scenarios where it's not really
where the numbers are whacked you know
in a way that kind of messes it up yeah
you know and I think about this in equal
value coin joints right there is there
is no discrepancy here right so so that
would be zero but then if you increase
the range of real values of these UT
axles that you have and it's it's more
volatile for example in between a
corridor of 1.1 Bitcoin and 0.9 Bitcoin
in this corridor plus minus 10% around
0.1 big around one Bitcoin you you can
have a range or you know this range
increases then to the plus minus 200
percent or whatever ok can we find some
method to calculate where this line of
you know range between the amounts shall
be said yeah I don't know maybe it's a
tough question
the thing with even if you have like a
value that's let's say more than twice
as big as the others but it still could
be hard to figure out like you know if
you have a hundred inputs there to be
many ways to get that to get that large
output so yeah these are good questions
and hard questions I think and I think
we would probably find that as the range
expands away from the equal output it it
reduces
one thing I want to bring up is that
knapsack was actually one of of the few
candidates for a one-way function I'm
just reading here in the Merkel Hellman
knapsack cryptosystem but it was later
rejected that's an interesting thing
because in that crypto system the users
the the the the user that wanted to
encrypt the data chose the elements in
the knapsack so that means he or she
could have chosen the absolutely best
elements to hide and mask the subset-sum
problem and it was still rejected so
this to me seems like a red flag I'm
just curious what would Ethan I would
say about that so I don't I don't know
much about the actual knapsack
cryptosystem I know it's been proposed a
number of times and I think generally my
understanding of it is the the problem
is that it is not of equal hardness so I
might choose a key or some secret value
that I think is is hard but then later
it turns out not to be hard um so
usually when you build crypto systems
you want something where the keys are
all a randomly chosen key has the same
strength and other randomly chosen key
um and a lot of sort of like NP problems
have trivial cases and you may not
always know whether you've chosen a
trivial case or not right but you know
just to take a look at this we see that
they choose a super increasing sequence
of elements such that you know the next
element is always the sum of all the
previous elements this is ideal for
hiding in a knapsack because you have a
lot of possible numbers you can swap for
other numbers and it's obvious which
numbers you can swap for other numbers
and even then it was rejected so it
seems are quite
me for us if we aren't able to you know
handpick the the it's not what we want
to want to hide in I guess if no it's
gonna pick it up then I might as well
say my bit first of all I'd like to
apologize him a bit sick and more
scatterbrained and cranky than usual so
I didn't really prepare properly and I
have a slight correction to hapara which
is that I do not like talk about any
talk about cash fusion in particular
more generally about this same problem
of assuming that this is like a valid
hardness assumption from a cryptographic
standpoint like interpreting the bell
numbers as security parameter seems
sketchy to me for these reasons and it
seems more sketchy to me also because I
think subset-sum is the wrong framing
for this I mean it's more like it I
think technically it's the end partition
problem and
subset-sum is a search problem but
really in the end partition problem is
also a search problem but from like a
China adversary point of view really
it's more of an optimization problem is
that maybe they only care about one
participant or maybe they only need
approximate answers so I think it's very
important to distinguish between the
number of plausible interpretations for
a coin during transaction for the equal
amount cases it's trivial it's literally
just a bill number but in in other cases
it seems like a very optimistic and of
assumption
to to like analyze the search space
invalid mappings from using the knapsack
terminology because that numbers might
not be relevant at all maybe because
they're using you know a better
proximate techniques for example linear
programming is pretty effective at
giving it a good enough but not perfect
solutions to this so that is the
resource for this research club was
actually using linear programming and he
could not not do anything with it so
yeah that's exactly the point I was
getting to by the way I used it as well
for the still yet unfinished shame
research that I did on on wasabi to
identify change so I did it's a pretty
effective technique I mean even for
wasabi sites coin joints when you have
the constraint set up right the system
like pulp with I don't remember I think
I used the coin horror solver whenever
it was not buggy it was under a second
to come up with an assignment that
that's unique for the the change values
even accounting for all of the stuff
that the wasabi coordinator does with
fee discounts and so on and so forth so
even for fairly large problems where n
is large in practice I think treating
the the space of invalid options is a
dangerous assumption and what James's
are equal showed was basically the
there's more than one solution and I
think that that's the number that we are
really interested as far as the privacy
gains because that's that's not
something that you can decide a priori
which of the valid solutions are correct
once you've enumerated a set of
solutions if that set is sufficiently
large that it confers
plausible deniability to the
participants then I think the coin joint
assumptions work so to meet kind of like
that is the that was the main point of
my email and was not you know with
respect to cash fusion but more
generally about knapsack and and cash
fusion I just want to jump in on that
idea that the number of solutions is the
privacy gained because with tumbled MIT
when using tumble bit as a payment hub
that is exactly the privacy definition
we get like any any any the privacy is
the number of ways that this input and
output relationship can be satisfied I I
think that that's like a really good way
of looking at it and that's not to say
that adding additional difficulty for
the adversary is bad I think it's great
to make it computationally harder I mean
I really struggled to write that linear
programming stuff because of all the
idiosyncrasies in wasabi and I'm still
not done there's still bugs so in a
sense it's effective but it's not a
robust security assumption I think all
right so so far we talked about
computational hardness one thing before
we move on to the actual number of valid
partitions I just want to address
something but because on the bit kind of
mailing list many people can be the basa
beings and just just like you now but
the wasabi example is bad because we
have Cohen selection that's very public
so if I look at inputs in a Vasavi
transaction and I if I find an input
that is larger than the based on
denomination then I'm not going to try
to find all the different partitions
these inputs can be combined together in
order to find a change but no I'm gonna
say hey this input is its own partition
I'm looking for the change for this
specific input and usually that's going
to be right unless this was a test
transaction
by me there were some strange noises
there but you see there there are very
very simple heuristics how to get the
change back because there are rules that
possibly follows and and that can be
used for for analyzing it yeah that's
exactly what I did I did not attempt to
analyze the mix outputs only the change
outputs but that that's still a large N
and in principle by specifying is a
linear constraints problem the search
space is the entire thing so I think
that there's a what the knapsack paper
basically did is it proposed a way of by
construction always having some
plausible deniability and my
understanding of cash Fusion is that it
kind of achieves the same plausible
deniability as James Bond's article
should stochastically in the sense that
given the amounts are quite similar and
there's randomization and many inputs
there's a very high probability that
there's going to be plausible
deniability but I think that's very
distinct from the computational hardness
of actually like putting assignments in
there yeah all right let's move on to
that because that's the this is the huge
contribution of of this because no one
actually ever thought about as far as I
know the knob stock paper introduced the
computational hardness idea but no one
thought about oh there are actually very
accidental valid submitting saying and
how does that make sense
now I there is an intuition that I heard
from John art and this is the birthday
problem right which actually John had
which would you like to explain the
birthday problem and how this can be
this intuition can be applied to the two
developed combinations maybe yeah I
forget where came up in
in which conversation but it's just I
guess the birthday paradox is kind of
just an example of how sometimes math
can be a little bit counterintuitive and
you don't expect like Oh 23 people in a
room well you know there's like a it
doesn't sound like that many people
right so it's when you hear that oh
there's a 50-50 chance that someone's
gonna have the same birthday
you kind of scratch your head and say
wait a sec does that make any sense
and so the same thing kind of the same
kind of counterintuitive property seems
to apply the here also when you look at
like it's surprising how many different
ways that the things can add up to the
same sums so there's a there's a piece
of code that mark wrote which which kind
of does like I just call it mini cash
fusion where he's just taking three
players that each have six in inputs
like any each of them are kind of like
they're they're pretty small like a 150
or 400 or something and then you run the
code and it's like oh there's like 60
ways that these could all add up and it
just seems like like really
counterintuitive and like for me I do
like just check a few of them like wow
okay that adds up like so you know that
you get a lot more things that sum up
and then you would really think I have a
question when we talk about plausible
deniability are we saying that the three
possible input-output relationships that
can be satisfied work or are you saying
that they're equally likely like you
like one could imagine that you have
three different ways of doing it
we've based on the spin distributions
one of the ways is like you know 98% of
the time and then the other two ways are
like one percent of the time why would
why would some of them be only one
percent versus one of them is like
ninety percent so if you imagine that
the number of input
coming into a transaction is like drawn
from a some sort of random function if
that random function is not like uniform
most people might only contribute three
inputs so five inputs is like less
likely but yeah I don't know it's an
interesting question I don't know I
think I mean if you look if I look at a
my wallet right now like some of the
some of the cash fusions have like like
you know three or four inputs some of
them have no input so it's I think it's
I don't know if that's gonna be too much
of a factor I just wanted a bit I wanted
to make a couple other comments of some
of these things you guys were saying um
I I forget who said it but I agree you
know the like the math and cash Fusion
is not exactly that the subset-sum
problem and it's not exactly the
partition problem either it's kind of
related to both of them but it's
slightly different I think it's kind of
it gets into like maybe what some people
will call like additive combinatorics
which I don't so I don't think there's
like a clear I don't think anyone's
really solved the math in like a
rigorous way now the other thing I
wanted to say is as far as the James
Watt I hope I'm pronouncing his name
right his paper is really interesting
but like to me it just basically all it
really proves is that it's not broken it
in a trivial way so what he's doing is
like just coming up with one possible
set of inputs and outputs and then
looking at all the other inputs and kind
of proving that they could at least
exist in some other in some other sum
but he's not he's not showing that
they're all like adding up at the same
time so he's kind of taking a slice you
know what I mean which is cool but it's
not really like proving anything one way
or the other I interpreted it as
concrete proof of so first of all to
clarify I used plausible deniability
the weaker sense of not assuming any
prior knowledge and only considering a
single transaction and isolation and
within that kind of like the way I
interpreted his article is that even
when you apply linear programming to
cash fusion transactions if you add if
you get a solution out of the solver and
then add a constraint that says it must
not be that solution additional
solutions exist and that's just a
standard technique for enumerated the
the set of solutions and to me the point
of it was even though the hardness
assumption might not be robust in the
sense of like interpreting the the
anonymity gained as proportional to the
Bell number you still end up with that
like fundamental level of ambiguity
because multiple solutions exist so I
understood like that to be a pretty
strong statement about he didn't analyze
like how it came to be that there were
multiple solutions but I thought it was
completely independent solutions based
on my understanding of his article well
he was showing that if you if you have
like one like out of the whole trend
this whole huge fusion transaction if
you like select some inputs and some
outputs he proved that the other inputs
like it's not unique like those those
inputs could be in some other sum but he
didn't really show that that both of
those would exist at the same time
that's that's kind of how I saw it so it
is like valuable to show it's not
trivially broken but it's also not like
a rigorous proof that it's you know that
it's secure
specifically the passage I'm referring
to so he says to check this we can rerun
the integer programming solver to try
and find a match that is distinct from
the match that we've already found the
must include this value when you said
he's not talking about the whole
transaction he's just talking about one
player as far as I understood it but
that implies that there's likes to at
least two valid interpretations based
just on the information inside of the
transaction so I think that's a pretty
good finding in the sense that like I
don't think it's any weaker just because
he's focusing on one was like one match
yeah maybe I mean I actually don't know
that much about linear programming but
yes it's pretty cool pretty cool how we
coded that I have a question about the
privacy model it is the assumption that
the tumbler or the party constructing
the coin joined the coordinator doesn't
know how many outputs are assigned to a
user so does it know that like three of
these outputs are the same user and two
of these outputs are a different user
it might not know their input-output
relationships but doesn't know the
groupings or does it know like this was
constructed by three users but it
doesn't know how many of those three
users are there and if that isn't in the
privacy model Oh
if that isn't assumes like what's the
network security to sort of hide that
from the from the like coordinator party
that's producing the when you win so the
server could find out how many players
are in a fusion but it doesn't know like
how many outputs or if there are like
per user does that answer it yeah I'm
just like how does it so I guess all
right so it knows how many are there
so the probability the the analysis like
if we say we have
deniability but one of those paths is
like assumes eight users and we know
that it's Lyme users do we still have
multiple debility like is there sort of
a little bit of trust as based on a
tumbler not to reveal that information
oh and all the users know this
information tour I believe not the area
the user is on now actually is another
users don't know I I'm not 100% sure but
if they're not something with the index
number in the blaine face to which of
the with which was the users your
randomly assigned an index number I
believe for them
that's not player based is just input so
when in the blame feeds you you know the
player is verifying one of the inputs or
one of the outputs but the the players
don't know how many other players
exactly are in the in the round the
server could know because because it has
the list of commitments from each player
but as far as like trying to like use
that information to get a better
understanding of the combinatoric s--
i think you'll probably only have a
limited value limited like you could
like if you're doing the math based on
sterling numbers it would narrow it down
like if you knew there was a eight
players exactly then it would just be it
would be like the Sterling number of
like eight Lauren let's say 250 inputs
then you could basically be asking how
many partitions are there with exactly
eight groups of 50 inputs and then the
same thing for the outputs so we
definitely decrease the number of dollar
partitions if you do that but only the
server knows that actually yeah thank
you
I I want to go back for a while when
when Ethan said something because I
think that was very important and we
kind of missed it that you know what
really matters is not the number of
parties
but how well the links are broken so the
nutsack paper actually gave a
mathematical model of analyzing Cohen
joins in terms of so if you take well
the valid partitions and then you look
at input input input output and output
output links which would mean that for
example you take two inputs and you see
how many valid partitions
there are compared to the total number
of valid partitions and that's how
strongly the link is broken
so I think when someone will investigate
this problem further then that would be
a very very useful thing to actually
look at and try to try to analyze it
because if it turns out that that the
valid partitions are usually the if it
turns out that that there are much more
valid partitions for for real link then
that's going to be the assumed
transaction there I hope it was
understandable what I said you asked me
are you saying that it's it's all about
just like finding the number of valid
partitions not necessarily the total
number of partitions if I register to
input together and no one knows these
two inputs are together but I registered
them together and then they find all the
valid partitions of the coin join and
then they find that that there are ten
valid partitions but out of that ten
nine valid partitions actually
partitions together my two inputs right
something that's almost as hard as like
trying to try to solve the basic problem
anyway it's like you're trying to you
have so many partitions it's really hard
to give that data I mean that's is there
I don't think that it is because I mean
again you have mecan't solve the
partition problem in the general case in
less than exponential time but for
special cases you often can and I think
that this is this is also a weakness of
the like the samurai Boltzmann entropy
measure I think that's another very
important distinction I want to draw is
like the privacy from the point of view
of an individual user so how much
plausible deniability am i gaining by
participating in a joint coin joint of
some form versus I guess technical
fungibility would be the way to frame it
that is how much does this transaction
how much I'm B get a does this
transaction create from a public point
of view and I think that those are very
distinct analyses because for privacy
you care about whether or not people are
targeting you and in those circumstances
it's also plausible that they're going
to use additional information like
network level privacy leaks they're
going to look at the transaction graph
as a whole and they don't really care
about looking at the parts of the
transactions that maybe you participated
in that don't pertain to that data so
that there's many ways to prune that
search space and and secondly maybe they
don't even care about like all they want
to prove is you know it the
that you had at least this much money
that flowed through some some something
right that's I think of a very different
analysis than the public level privacy
which is what most of these analyses
kind of kind of look at did that make
sense yeah interesting points yeah
you're talking about using other like
you said no network level there could be
timing things yeah there's like
different ways that people could try to
try to break the privacy but yeah it's
it's kind of an interesting it brings up
the discussion of like you know how much
privacy do we need or maybe it's good to
like not have like too much like maybe
not hat you know like in Bitcoin cache
like we don't necessarily want to become
Manero for example so maybe there's like
a good balance where a coin can have
like the privacy for everyday users and
still not be like no be like that go too
far on the side of privacy where the
regulators hate it I don't know well I
mean even in maneras case if you have
some requirement you can always prove
what you actually did so that's not the
distinction I'm trying to draw rather
that there if we assume that privacy and
fungibility are Anette good analyzing
the risk or as uncertainty with respect
to either feels very different to me
because for the case of one user trying
to hide from an adversary that sees
everything a lot of these guarantees
that make sense
in kind of the public context become a
much weaker in in like a single user
context yeah yeah we're agree but it's
like you can look at the average you can
imagine a coin joint that provides very
good average privacy but always Rob's
one user of privacy
and so if you just look at that average
you're like oh it's providing a lot of
privacy but if you're that one user you
get no privacy from it so I think yeah
like what is the minimum privacy
provided to each user um right rather
than like the average privacy provided
oh yeah that's the point that is trying
to make yeah go back to that example
where there's like two inputs even if
you group them together that doesn't
necessarily tell you what the outputs
are so maybe neck that's kind of part of
the conversation of the minimum can you
rephrase that I didn't understand like
even if you even if you somehow were
able to determine that there was some
inputs that are likely to belong to the
same person that doesn't necessarily
tell you which outputs they got right
but I think that in that scenario it was
like there are ten valid ways for this
coin joining to work and in nine of them
this set of two inputs matches some
other set of three outputs and then in
another only one other case for that set
of inputs matches and other set of
outputs so if you were to assume that
these inputs and outputs were selected
but randomly there is only a 10% chance
points one place and there's a 90%
chance particular input-output
relationship for a particular user oh
that's actually the exact same problem
that's the largest input largest output
attack what you you mentioned Janet
which was which was what some 100 1000
and everyone ask comes with around one
right so one thousand in and I don't
know 900 out that can be only that
because in every valid sub mapping of
the coin join that large input will all
connect to that large output right but
but in the case we're not talking about
like those kind of outliers I mean like
how would you how would you solve this
how would you how would you get insights
into which are the which inputs go
together so I don't know how you would
get insights like in the largest value
one it's like pretty obvious but there
might be some of them less less obvious
approaches but I think that the right
metric to use to measure the amount of
privacy is to look at the the guessing
entropy that is if you sorted all the
possible input-output valid input-output
relationships from most likely to least
likely and you started guessing from
most likely how many guesses would you
need before you got to the correct
answer like on average but there's
multiple correct answers right there's
multiple correct answers but some of the
correct answers are more likely to be
correct than other ones hmm like in the
nine versus one example when user gets
in anonymity set size too and the other
user gets where the other users get much
higher values right what you users and
high value users and even if they put
the money into the same coin join the
the low and high value users are going
to end up in the same sub mappings in
every every village sub mapping of the
coin joints or most of them it'll be
interesting to see what people come up
with you know some some actual
mathematicians maybe will publish a
paper and see they will see some more
insights into the heuristics and
techniques like that could be used to
try to break it how would this change if
we have a combination of unequal and
equal output in one transaction
basically something like what wasabi is
doing right now
right you have the equal value and you
have change but differing from this
current model to remove this restriction
on the number of inputs and outputs so
basically say that any one user must
have at least one input and at least one
output but there is no upper bound
basically with question some some reason
and then you don't know his one user has
only unequal amounts or if he also has
equal amount coins and how would this
change the the possible set well already
you can have multiple I mean you can as
far as the second part of what you said
like there's no you know the only thing
is there's 23 is the maximum total of
inputs plus outputs so you could have
one input one output but you could have
also have more inputs or or or outputs
but then as far as having some of the
outputs being the same value it's kind
of interesting a network that's I never
thought about that but maybe it's maybe
I can improve it so here is a thought I
wanted to bring up later but now we are
on topic that if we would want to use
cash fusion as it is then without cash
off or without any kind of mixing before
then you would still have to break coins
into two or three or four parts anyway
don't you because it's like users don't
have like only users who would have a
lot of volume and incoming and outgoing
money would be able to actually
participate with multiple inputs and
outputs so I think some kind of amount
splitting would be necessary in order to
keep the thing flowing do you have any
think is that something miss am I on the
right path on this thinking
that's the whole benefit of like the
unequal amounts you don't need to worry
about splitting things and and trying to
like prepare the UT EXO's you can just
kind of fuse with whatever coins came
from the last region or or whatever you
have so it's yeah kind of more practical
there is a difference there because in
unequal amount you cannot split that's
the rule here you would split and you
would gain privacy but you would have
you could still decide to not split it
so that's that's why it's interesting
you know all the stuff is pretty
interesting yeah okay anyway let's move
on to two there are three attacks the
type I wrote to myself and one is we
talked about the largest input largest
output the other two is his Eaton's
attack shocks actually
but for before going into eternal attack
anyone has any idea how to mitigate the
largest input largest output attack well
like I was saying earlier if there's if
there's some kind of a sanity check on
the server before it it proceeds if
there's an outlier where it's some huge
value that's that's an order of
magnitude beyond everything else it
could just maybe the round just gets
aborted or something yes and I think
that the robot is described in the paper
with the spear size or cool read history
so I think very interesting because here
then we can use different polls to see
who is waiting for doing a coin join and
then as soon as a certain and onset is
reached that specific tea arrange of
let's say one Bitcoin plus minus 10%
gets done by then maybe the the lower
the ranges maybe 10 become plus minus 1
percent like the the more possible sub
mappings would be valid
so how would you define the outlier my
thinking is that it is larger than the
sum of all the other inputs so there is
an output that's larger than the sum of
all the other inputs but there might be
some more restriction needed there so it
sounds like a sensible upper bound at
least right yeah by the way these other
attacks where can I read about them I
haven't I haven't he said that he
thought a couple of attacks where can we
find this so it is on the wasabi
research Club it is pointing to the
Bitcoin dev mailing list and there were
some discussion and and let's see and
okay so so one of the attack is the
precision attack eaten could you
describe it sure so I should I should
preface my statement by the the stuff
that I read through on confusion wasn't
very specific on how it worked so I made
some assumptions about how it works
those assumptions may not be correct so
the first attack was assuming that we
allow inputs of arbitrary precision and
looking at C so looking at the precision
of the outputs where you can you can
infer based on say like this having a
whole bunch of decimal places
it could only be or then it was more
likely than it was from a particular
input so like if you had an input that
was like one dot 0 0 0 0 0 0 1 and then
you had an output that also had like
like that was like you know 0.5 0 0 0 1
if the it's probably likely that that
one that's all the way out to the right
matches in the output matches in that
input
so I looked at that if you just allow
arbitrary arbitrary precision especially
if you're doing wallets where some of
the wallets may not actually allow you
to do outputs of arbitrary precision um
I don't know if this is a problem in
Bitcoin but I know in aetherium and
their people sometimes don't let you do
beyond a certain level of precision so
you might have wallets where some
wallets are only producing input outputs
with a certain level of precision and
then all their wallets are producing
input-output relationships with a a
higher level of precision um so this
could this could be a heuristics that
would allow you to identify input-output
relationships I don't know if that made
any sense just to be clear it's it's a
good attack vector except if there's any
randomization in the fees it would
distort any minut differences in the in
the you know eighth and seventh and six
decimal points so that's just my I'm
guessing that's what jonald would say as
well yeah I agree it's easy to mitigate
ways to yeah I mean that's what we're
already doing I think just a trivial
amount I think I got just ten Satoshi's
of randomness with the fees but we could
add more and we could also add like just
kind of like any mark calls of
quantizing just just kind of bird
forcing like just chopping off a decimal
to make it just have less precision in
the outputs it just makes it a lot
harder to to have unique ways to add up
or makes they're more possibilities for
different combinations to add up
you've seen these mixing protocols you
can all be is up to let's let's take one
person fee from everyone and that fee
would be some some gambling there that
to make make make make output somehow
equal or something like that that would
be the the point of the fees
there are there are interesting things
that are eaten do you agree that it's
easy to me take it I think that the the
mitigation described like breaks my
attack um but I'm not sure that there
isn't a more advanced attack and it
really depends how you do these like
fees because if you're you know like if
the if the fees were only to a certain
level a precision and and the output was
the the the precision that someone
produced it out put in it was like
greater than the fees so I think it
really depends on on how exactly these
mitigations work well when I wrote that
attack as I said before um I wasn't sure
on some of the details with how the
protocol works oh it's just assuming
arbitrary I was assuming two cases
either arbitrary precision or on a fixed
precision and then I looked at attacks
against both of them but I did not
consider that case in which you are like
randomly subtracting fiends which is a
is a really interesting approach but I
think kind of I need to think about it
more to understand that um how whether
it fully mitigates it but it does
mitigate the like sort of fully attack I
posted a reckon by the way I think a
slightly more robust mitigation would be
to not just add fuzzing would also
restrict the Hamming weight where is
something proportional to the product of
the Hamming weight which is just a
number of one bits in or the number of
symbols needed to represent an amount
times the difference between the largest
figure and the smallest figure because
that that gives you the the formula is
just off the top of my head please don't
take it literally but the idea there
being the more the the larger the
Hamming weight of an amount the more a
signal there is in there so that's a
very simple approach to
kind of reduce the ability of the
adversary to interpret the the different
bits in the the amounts as related or
not related to each other maybe what
Hamming is because when I wrote that
I've heard it before and I've seen it so
it's the number of symbols required to
represent a codeword and in the context
of amounts well you can just think of it
as the number of 1 bits given that the
alphabet is like binary digits and so
for example if you represent a power of
2 of satoshis that's gonna be a Hamming
weight of 1 where is like a high
precision value with many digits in it
that's gonna have a much higher Hamming
weight I guess it sounds very related to
just have any decimal precision I think
that that's one aspect but also the the
other aspect is within that range of
precision how much information is in
that amount like it could be a very
precise amount in the sense that there's
a very large difference between the most
significant digit and the least
significant digit but if those are the
only two digits then you only need a
very minor amount of fuzzing so long as
for the most significant digit you have
plausible deniability because of the
other participants right that's right
assume that there is a everybody is on
the same tier therefore everybody's
amounts are within the same order of
magnitude that confers plausible
deniability to the most significant
digits and fuzzing confers possible
deniability to the least significant
digits but you know for larger amounts
there's a disincentive to enable it but
if you restrict the number of digits
that appear in the middle of the range
then you only need a small amount of
fuzzing to basically make it so that
that information is is kind of useless
to anybody doing this sort of analysis
did that make sense yeah yeah I wish
mark was on this call cuz I'm sure he'd
get a lot a lot from that I think as as
we go on evolving this thing there'll be
lots of things we can we can add in to
try to improve just like the the
consistency of getting quality fusions
that that are all well you know or that
are more private in general so yeah
maybe we can we can use some of those
techniques to to try to do that yeah
thanks and how about I talk to Eaton
because I have to admit I've read it
many times but this made absolutely no
sense for me can you elaborate on what
what it's about Eaton sorry yeah I kept
machine the me button I'm sure I think I
think one mistake I was making when
analyzing it was I was not um I was
assuming that the I was not assuming
that someone was adding more than one
input but I think that the attack still
works but I'm gonna modify it a little
bit um so the idea is that rather than
deal with lots of this rather than deal
with arbitrary precision you fix
precision um but since you fix precision
you have cases in which for example
here's a really trivial case imagine
that you fixed precision to be only one
or two bitcoins well if you have if all
your outputs are are on then you know
that every single one of those outputs
must Elise map to one of
the one inputs because to be an odd
number it must have one if you're
drawing from the set of one did you so
if you have like a very small number of
inputs that are similar you can make
these inferences that allow you to sort
of shortcut trying every single
possibility you're set to be the numbers
one through five so you can only have
inputs of the numbers one through five
and you're looking at an output and the
output is an odd number then that must
mean that the input set of that output
must contain either one three or five
it must contain at least one odd number
because two even number even numbers
added together it should never result in
an odd number what does that still hold
up if under the in the context of having
an arbitrary number of outputs let's see
um he split it no that doesn't hold up
in having an arbitrary number of outputs
because you would split the even split
you could split an even number into two
outputs yeah so I think I was thinking
about the I think when I was thinking
about my infusion I was thinking it was
more like some of the previous
approaches where you have like inputs to
outputs like you don't hear or not like
splitting the inputs and you're
outputting the outputs so the example
that I know that there was was exactly
that ten inputs then users every one
with ten
inputs and exactly one output that was
the example so that's so if you know how
many users participate and how many
inputs user participate feed or how many
output a user create then that would
then that gives gives assumptions like
this gives gives more more power for
assumptions like this it's it's actually
pretty genius yeah and the the tumbler
might might know that is value is right
we might know how many users there are
and actually so I asked this before but
I've forgotten the answer does the
tumbler know that a particular user
created not does the tumbler knew that a
user exists that created three outputs
they might not know which out listeners
are and they might not know which user
created those outputs but do they know
that there is a group of three outputs
and are now the server doesn't know the
server does not know how many how many
inputs or outputs each player brought I
mean every obviously everyone sees the
completed transaction and knows the
total inputs and outputs of the entire
transaction but not even the server
knows like that Alice brought seven
inputs in three and three outputs or
something but the you know like I would
deserver might not know that Alice did
three inputs and seven outputs but the
server might know that someone created
seven outputs now they but they don't
though all right this is because the
various components are not linkable
right each is submitted on a separate
channel the server has 23 component
commitments from every user but those
commitments don't
much and the input and the input
components and output components and the
blank commitments are both registered in
different tour streams or not not as one
so so there there is there may be
something in a blaming phase but but
other than that not nothing Suman said
tour circuit per employee exactly it's a
tour circuit per to cut it and then
during the blank phase it's just
basically one one component gets checked
but and then the round like reduces the
number players for the one for that one
person all right so my very last
question of the day and and I let her
keeper to talk to so are you guys
familiar with shared coin block chaining
for was was was creating that in 2013
which was unequal inputs and unequal
outputs that of course the blockchain
info server know everything but
regardless crystal fat loss was able to
do some conjoined pseudo coup and so
what was the problem with shared coin
well the problem there is the linear
programming so there is a special case
of linear programming so that that was
able to solve it very efficiently and in
practice in many of the cases because
typically users would have one input and
one output if you have you can you can
do sorry one I think they had like in a
typical case one input and an output and
a change output
my bad
oh okay yeah oh yes because I was
actually using shape okay when I was
using it I had to I always sent the
money which shared Kareem I never mix to
myself yeah it's a indeed SharePoint
work is that is it similar like there's
a server like wasabi no so it doesn't
work
it worked for a couple of years but it
got shut down its block chaining
varieties of a bullet and blockchain
so I trust less you couldn't lose your
money but there were no privacy
guarantees because the server did
everything all right
aviv igor max all Garofalo we have a lot
of people here yeah yeah so you guys
feel free to join in and ask questions
or topics I didn't rota I sort of wanted
to I guess ask a few questions to
journaled
but rather if someone who hasn't spoken
yet wants to ask first go ahead okay I
guess I will go ahead so I just want to
get a better understanding of the larger
picture of how cache fusion was intended
to work in practice so just just a few
questions and hopefully you can answer
them so typically users show up with
more inputs than helpless right the idea
is to fuse inputs into outputs so that
was the original idea but it sort of
evolved to now it's kind of like a
general-purpose many-to-many coin joint
so some some transactions could be
fanning in when I say fanning enemy
there's
outputs and inputs and some could be
fanning out where there's more outputs
and inputs and then within one of those
there could be like Alice could be
Fanning in about could be fanning out at
the in the same fusion so it's kind of
become this like this general-purpose
thing where each of the wallets has like
just a bunch of UT X OS and it just kind
of there was there's a little bit of
randomness where it selects you know
like let's say 10 inputs and then it's
just going to decide randomly you're
gonna get eight outputs CNN I'm doing
like a 10 day and then in the next round
maybe you're gonna go the other one
you're gonna start with like five inputs
and you'll get 13 outputs so it's kind
of a little bit random I think what
we're gonna do is try to try to make
some like user friendly settings in the
wallet so that it it would like fuse a
bunch do a bunch of rounds and then at
the end it would try to click
consolidate them down so you have less
less coins so let's say I'm a user right
I show up with let's say I just withdrew
all my big win cash from the exchange
and so now I'm using this cash fusion
system so it's going to start fanning
out and I'm guessing it's also running
in the background if I leave my laptop
just awake and I just let it run it's
going to keep mixing in these different
transactions correct yeah that brings up
an interesting point which is like you
know if you just let it run forever it
is it just gonna eat all your all your
money and fee is so so we we think we
need some kind of thing where it does
shut off eventually
and then maybe there's another mode for
like liquidity providers I just want to
just you know keep it open although
there's well we can talk about large
amounts like 10 big win cash and 100 for
example where something like this
wouldn't wouldn't really matter
although you know you can't run it
infinitely so then I want to spend money
what does that look like am i looking at
my you see episode sets and just
selecting a bunch of UT exomes to spend
so okay so you're talking about coin
selection after you've already done a
bunch of fusions yes yes no I think like
ideally you don't spend all of the
claims from a single fusion together
because that's sort of it's sort of a
sliding scale like you know the absolute
best thing is to spend one you TXO
because then you're you're leaking zero
information right and then when you spit
at the opposite end of that is if you
spend all the UT EXO from a fusion it
just it kind of degrades that fusion for
the other players so maybe there's
something weird like warns you or it's
like hey are you sure you want to spend
this it's like it's kind of a low of
privacy spend but on the other hand we
don't want to like prevent people of you
know it's your money you want to spend
it and you should be able to spend those
coins so the wallet should kind of
ideally be smart enough to you know to
try to coax the user to doing it a
little more privately with also having
the flexibility of just letting you
spend freely if you think you can you
can spend within the coin fusion or the
cap screws right that's what I'm gonna
miss that was sort of like the only
problem with that is that you you might
have to wait like if I want to buy
something let's say I wanna buy a domain
name so I going Namecheap I could I
could like set that up somehow but then
it's gotta wait until that fusion
happens so that may or may depending on
the liquidity like it made in my feature
right right and it might be a different
tier size by the tier size was rather
low and limit is that for example or low
number of tiers or whatever metric we
will use and and that just completes
faster right and then you have something
every ten minutes even if it's only ten
different users that will be alright in
the span
maybe there's a feature that we want to
eventually but I don't think we're going
to do it right away and I don't want to
ask too many questions because it'll go
on forever so maybe just two one more
after I've done my first fusion and I
get let's say six outputs the next
fusion that I get into does the software
limit how many outputs from the past
fusion are going to be allowed into the
next fuschia what does that look like to
get a question I mean it basically does
a random selection so if that's all you
have is those six outputs that it would
probably use them but I guess ideally
it's it's trying to try to be a little
bit random so it you know if you have a
hundred each EXO might take you know ten
for round one and then a different set
for round two maybe round two has a few
of them but yeah I think it's just it
just has to be random okay
so it just become a problem for people
with a small you TXO set so the it's not
that private event as they as they keep
using they'll just they'll get a bigger
set of more like kind of truly random
coins got it okay I'll leave it at that
thank you so much you had jonald for
answering those questions yeah sorry I
don't have like perfect answers for
these things but and so we have here
developers mathematicians a
cryptographer
and even a woman how you guys see some
of this stuff do you see it being ported
over to DPC in some form
I think I'm I am really in doubt here
because because it's it's something that
you know that there is something out
there that's already working and and it
might very well be just just working and
sound and it might very well be the
actual best privacy solution for Bitcoin
Bitcoin cash doesn't matter but on the
other hand I'm somewhat afraid - well
okay let's go a hundred percent forward
on on unequal Cohen joins because there
are just so many little things that I'm
not that smart you know I'm just a
programmer and I'm not sure I would be
able to even believe if there would be
one research out there that would go
through it maybe there would be to say
yeah I'm in doubt because on the one
hand I want to innovate and on the other
hand and just what if I up
something people are relying on this
really heavily and that's scary you know
so I I don't know like there's some
things in the samurai wallet like
ricochet and a stowaway do you think are
also pretty cool that maybe we'll adopt
it you know in Bitcoin cash I think well
there's like there's like you hear these
things it's about the coin joint
flagging so which is pretty stupid but
it's like maybe maybe some tools like
ricochet would be good too you know to
have it's let's not debate samurai
like oh she has a very unique
fingerprint on the back chain you're
just losing less and spending okay
that's not no no it's just we'll talk
about that a different different time so
ask your earlier question are we going
to use this I would say maybe this is a
bit different than whatever then with no
power set which is that we are trying to
get inspiration from all ideas so it's
very likely that we will take some
subset of the ideas that you've come up
with and and we might find a place for
them Oh a very very important
interesting thing eaten in Tom Babbitt
you were fighting with how to make sure
that the tumblr parameters the tumblr is
not lying about its parameter do you
remember yeah and you were coming up
[Music]
anyway could you mute yourself for a
little bit thank you so cache fusion has
a pretty cool way to to answer that the
tumblr parameters are not lies it's
actually in an Oprah turn of the coin
join the the hash of the the tumblr
parameters and actually you can extend
this this idea to more generically that
every oh my god I don't really remember
but every input has to sign that yeah
there is something about that that you
might want to look at the issues of
cache fusion and and that that could I
don't know if that would be nice for
tumblr
it's interesting um I think that the
biggest parameter that we wanted to lock
in was the time at which the tumbles
occurred because if if you do them at a
particular set time then if you exclude
a bunch of people it's much more obvious
then if you do them like on the fly when
you have enough users you could be like
oh I want to target this person so I
just added a bunch of fake users and now
I'm gonna like mix with them but I think
this this protection against like civil
attacks where you where the tumbler is
malicious and adds users to create the
illusion of privacy is it's really
really hard to solve and I think taking
an approach where you just assume the
tumbler does not do that is probably
more realistic although it tumbled it
was attempting to prevent those sorts of
simple attacks yeah it's another kind of
worms here let's not open this okay so
what do you guys have or should we
should because this I have to go pretty
soon here so if anyone was to go then I
can leave first or otherwise I'm not
here I also chopped off in a few minutes
so was it was a good caller and thanks a
lot this was probably the most deepest
conversation of the wasabi research Club
ever so thank thank you guys it was
really awesome and yeah this is the
highlight of my week lately thank you
bye bye thanks guys thanks everyone
thank you it was a good